Preliminary Guide to the Faculty Women's Club records, 1930-1992 RG0085
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Faculty Women's Club records
1930-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0085
3.25 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include membership directories, program booklets, meeting minutes, constitution and by-laws, annual reports, scrapbooks (with clippings, invitations, programs, photographs). They range in date from 1930-1992.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred to the University Archives by the President of the Faculty Women's Club.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Faculty Women's Club at The George Washington University grew out of the parent organization the Columbian Women, formed in 1894 and continuing today. All women associated with the University as students or faculty were invited to belong to the Columbian Women. In 1930 the membership numbered 566, of which 82 were faculty or faculty wives. Feeling the need for closer friendship among the faculty wives, especially the newcomers, Mrs. John Donaldson held a series of small teas for getting acquainted. The Faculty Women's Club was formally founded February 21, 1931 at which time the By-Laws were passed and Mrs. John Donaldson was elected President. The club's purpose was to "foster friendliness and sociability among all of the women of the faculty and to cooperate in every possible way in promoting the interests of the University." Annual dues were set at twenty-five cents and membership was open to the "wife or recognized hostess of any faulty member, including Emeriti professors, and any woman member of the faculty." In the first year of 1931-32 ninety women joined as charter members, of which fifteen were faculty members.
During the war years the club's activities were curtailed, but in 1950 Mrs. Mitchell Dreese became president and amended the constitution to include as members the University Administrators and certain Research personnel. Extra effort was put into planning interesting programs, and to help newcomers get acquainted, special interest groups were formed which met at members' homes. From 1950-75 membership reached a high of 275 members in 1964 with an average of 210 during the period. After 1975 the membership declined, perhaps attributable to "an increase in female employment" (according to a history written in 1980).
In 1981 the club presented the University a ceremonial mace, to be used as official processions. President Elliott called it a "historic gift" and said that it would become a ceremonial part of the activities of the University. The Faculty Women's Club ceased functions around 1992.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include membership directories, program booklets, meeting minutes, constitution and by-laws, annual reports, scrapbooks (with clippings, invitations, programs, photographs). They range in date from 1930-92, and were transferred to the University Archives by the President of the Faculty Women's Club.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series of club records.
Washington (D.C.); Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Photographs; Women; Scrapbooks; Faculty; Students; Dreese, Mrs. Mitchell; George Washington University; Donaldson, Mrs. John; Columbian Women, George Washington University, Washington (D.C.)
- Club Records, 1930-1988; RG0085 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes membership lists, program booklets, meeting minutes, constitution and by-laws, annual reports, scrapbooks, and histories. They range in date from 1930 to 1988.
  Formerly ACC#19
  - Membership Lists, 1953-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Formation and Early History, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Program Booklets, 1953-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1958-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1958-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1958-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arts and Antiques Interest Group, Art Appreciation and Home Interests, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bible Study Interest Group, 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bridge Interest Group, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book Discussion Interest Group, 1965-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Theatre Interest Group, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Needleworking Group, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Constitution, Bylaws and Amendments, 1950 ca.-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Reports, 1967-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Program Chairman Reports, 1958-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Financial Reports, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Membership Committee, 1970 ca.-1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Faculty Student Relations, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Publicity, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hospitality, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hospitality, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Club Records, 1952-1992; RG0085 Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes membership and officers directories, meeting minutes, scrapbooks (with clippings, invitations, programs, photographs). They range in date from 1952-1992.
  Formerly ACC#1050
  - Faculty Women's Club, 1953-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Women's Club, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Women's Club, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Women's Club, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Women's Club meeting minutes, 02/11/1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Club records, 1932-1981; RG0085 Series 3; .25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes correspondence, memos, schedules, draft of constitution, histories, member lists and programs. They range in date from 1932-1981.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Clubs, Societies, Organizations--Faculty Women's Club, 1932-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clubs, Societies, Organizations--Faculty Women's Club - History, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clubs, Societies, Organizations--Faculty Women's Club Publications, 1955-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)